Noel Phyllis Birkby Papers, 1932-1994
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Man w/guitar in civic space. Two African-American men singing and playing guitar in New York. Footage good, not scratched. Street scene of VW red bus painted w/ "LOVE" in big white letters. Could be Washington Square. Hot dog stand, footage looks good, not scratched, minor anyway. Crowd in demonstration or someone's famous, huge crowd. It is Washington Square Park. Long shot. General long shot of people in park, child by pool, volleyball game at Washington Square Park. Red bus is in frame, may have carried the women into the park. Dark shot of game.
Next reel: Back to singers from first reel, strung together, good looking heterosexual older couple in their seventies. Series of shots of people sitting around circle w/fountain in middle in Washington Square Park. People dog walking in Washington Square Park. People sitting around a bench in the park. People gathering in small groups, crowd probably watching entertainers. Two women playing the viola, small group of musicians people watching. Two people (women?) under tree. Photographers, man and woman, sitting at tripod. Man w/sign on his back, ice cream stand. People sitting in small group w/ guitar. General Washington Square Park study.
77. MORE WASHINGTON SQ. PARK. 1.5 min.
Mainly of kids playing. A guy in a suit on a podium, kids playing tag, semi-soft focus.
78. WASHINGTON PARK STUDY SERIES 10/70.
Dog running, fall day, beautiful, no scratches. Pigeons, dogs, people in the street around the park. People walking dogs, squirrel.
79. WASHINGTON PARK STUDY SERIES II 10/70.
Mainly of the arch and buildings surrounding the park, dogs, fountain.
80. WASHINGTON PARK STUDY SERIES III 10/70. 1.5 min.
People in park kissing w/green film. Man filming, woman taking light reading, shooting a kid in a tree. Green filter, trees and sky. Then yellow filter. People reading w/yellow filter.
81. WASHINGTON PARK STUDY SERIES IV 10/70.
Small patch of snow in fall leaves. People around pond. Mounds in park. Twilight. Beautiful filter rainbow light coming down into park. Refraction of light through trees - very pretty. Pigeons on cement bricks. Pigeons in trees. Park bench empty, w/pigeons.
82. WASHINGTON PARK STUDY SERIES V 10/70.
10/25/70. Dark. Kid on bicycle. The arch. Looks like twilight. Fountain without water. Kids in the rain. Troubador area - sign on post.
83. WASHINGTON SQUARE PARK. (color and black and white)
Pan around stone steps or enclosure. Crowd shots from the back and side, panning around. Jump cuts between medium shots of people in crowd. Medium shot, pan out of man dancing. Wide shot, zoom in on child in fountain. Jump cuts between shots of black inverted cap-things on ground.
Cut to black and white footage. Children playing on jungle gym in med. long shot, their truncated limbs pass in and out of the spaces between the beams. Med. shot of parents or older children, from back. Med. long shot of children crawling on top of structure. Wide shot, of merry-go-round, zoom into child in center. Med. shot, framed by beams, of child smoking (?).
Cut to color footage. Med. shots of people in Washington Square.
Cut to black and white. Activities in W. Square: woman buys a glass pipe, woman combs hair, shots of people passing by. Elderly couple walzes in midst of passers by. Med. shot of their legs, knees-down, dancing. Zooms out to wide shot. Head shots of passers-by moving in and out of frame.
Cut to color. Shot of the upper half of arch in W. Square. Shots of people in Square, camera zooming in and out. Toddler chases ball.
84. WHOLEO. Original footage, 16 mm, 1751, unscratched, unprojected, perfect condition, tails out on reel.
Hammer's archive has similar footage shot by Hammer of Birkby at same time and in same place. Footage of stained glass Buckminster Fuller-type dome w/aluminum or metal struts. 1978 or 79. Good shape, no scratches, Barbara Hammer is in it. Circle pan of the dome, still shots of different configurations of the stained glass. Circular movement spinning you around the dome. At the Russian River in California. Camera pans by Barbara Hammer, nude shot of Hammer. Another one of Hammer showing necklace to someone and taking a coffee cup and putting a medallion in it. Hammer dramatically pouring tea. Colored reflection of glass on nude body. Hammer standing on head w/breasts sagging. Colored light playing over her body. Another circle spin of the stained glass.
One of the Tatami mats w/colored light reflected on it. Coffee cup is picked by woman who was living in the Dome [Caroling]. Beautiful outdoor shot of the dome going down to the entranceway. Shot looking in through the entranceway into the Dome. Shot of B. Hammer in the dome, talking, scratching back, gesturing. New interior space of wooden structure, The Pyramid [of Amaratasu], on top of hill in northern side of the mouth of the Russian River. Lived in and constructed by women. CU of a fuschia.
B. Hammer overexposed walking on a cliff by the beach, undressing, posing. Long shot of Hammer on cliffs w/water below. Ocean then back up to Hammer, stretching, on the cliff top. Dark footage. Ocean sunset, pinkish. Closeup of hand and flower and second shot is sideview of Hammer's face. A shot of Phyllis in same position, very intimate, camera moves into her eye and quickly down her body. CU of two hands and flower - more than a dozen short shots of Hammer's hands in different positions ending up w/camera movement, making the hands turn in a circle. Lovely.
85. WIND CHIMES. 11/71 8 mm.
Strips of different colored clay that look like pieces of cloth on a clothesline blowing in the wind. First shots are good, later overexposed, then good again. Second group of chimes made of glass jars w/little pieces of ceramic inside them to jangle with them. Don't know location. Good condition, no scratches.
86. WINDSOR PRINT. Approx. 15 min.
(Some dykes in nature.) Woman reading, eating. Overexposed badly, waterfall and Louise Fishman. Nicely exposed light reflection on water. More overexposed. Soft focus woman/lipstick- Frances Doughty? Foot in water. Nice black and white flicker abstraction. Dark. More abstraction. Back of woman in underpants - Louise Fishman- at waterfall; later front view. Out of focus and overexposed water. Is that Frances in profile? Water skeeter/nice radiating circles like moire patterns! Overexposed leaves. Some branches good, especially cutting. Louise Fishman drinking tea. Other dykes close ups. Same woman eating chips that film started with.
87. WINDSOR. Sup. 8 Color.
Woman eating potato chips reading typed papers like newspapers. Then a long shot of her in chair w/ portable typewriter. It's a well-known writer. Shot of dog w/ curly hair. Color shot of woman cut to same woman in B&W, sharp focus. Another woman w/dogs at creek. Next shot overexposed shots of creek. She edited this, no idea why she kept that in. Water shot of creek, good exposure. Again overexposed. Soft focus of Frances Doughty. Feet in water. Again, a lot of overexposed. (I think this is an edited film where she wanted to go between light and dark - doing this on purpose). Lots of water shots. Section of woman in nude except for red underpants whose holding up a rock in the water. Looks like it's Louise Fishman, it is. Camera zooms in to Louise Fishman laughing. Again more overexposed. Some beautiful CU abstractions of water. CU of a redhead from behind and then zoom out to woman in clothes in water, turns looks at camera, and zoom in on her. Long curly brown hair. Another woman drinking from a plastic cup. It's Lousie Fishman. That's soft focus. Then a real cute CU of Louise Fishman smiling, drinking from the cup in focus. Another woman who has a red bandana around her neck w/green cup. Another woman and back to the woman with the potato chips. Footage has one scratch going all the way through. It's a finished film, signed NP Birkby.
PERSONAL
88. "AMAZON WEEKEND". Completed Film, needs head leader. Aprox. 20 min. Super 8 mm.
Women at lake nude, washing hair, swimming. Beautiful exposure. Two scratches. Jill Johnston. Counter Revolution and Revolt. Sidney Abbott? Great CU JJ/freckles. Woman on float in water. Nicely lit. Stop Action overexposed. Long shot woman on float. Loving shot of two women topless with floats, hugging, kissing. Nice! Nude woman jumps onto float. and again but misses. It is Sidney Abbott or Phyllis Birkby. Or each. Jill. African American woman. Jane O'Wyatt. Jill with pen. Volleyball. Film Break.
Wine drinking. African American woman dancing, acting silly. More rafting. Two rafts. Smoking on raft. Film Break and crinkle.
89. "AMAZON WEEKEND. Print.
90. CR VOLLEYBALL. Super 8. Approx. 15 min.
Jane O'Wyatt. Kate Millett. All the women in the Consciousness Raising Group playing volleyball.
91. CR 1 VOLLEYBALL.
Kate Millett, a blond curly-haired woman [Linda Clarke] she had her arms around in the '71 womens march, Jane O'Wyatt, Sidney Abbott and others. Looks good, some scratches. She did a nice section of women's hands, nice section, while they were playing a game. Soft focus shot, long, long shot of Kate Millett laughing. Really nice shot of overall game. Long shot. Getting firewood, looks like Jane O'Wyatt is chopping wood, with an ax. Two shots of that.
92. CR #1 DINNER PARTY AT KATE MILLET'S FARM.
Dark, very dark, again a lot of close ups of women's faces but not well exposed. Not much useful. Maybe a party or a CR group, again very dark, maybe Barbara Love. A woman with a hand by her face. Is it too dark to tell. Nice shot of a woman's hand on a kitchen counter or table with glasses, wine glass, plate. That's Barbara Love. Good shot with hands on face. Nice shot of hand with cup. But, mainly too dark.
93. "DANCE" BIRTHDAY PARTY? JENNIFER. B&W 8 mm.
Turntable, outdoor street light. Jennifer's birthday party in B&W? Birthday cake. Kids blowing out candles. Kids outside w/ man. Birthday girl turning around, going over to her maybe little sister, holding her hand, two dance together, very, very cute CU of their faces.
94. "DYKES AT JILL'S WEEKEND".. aka JILL'S WEEKEND UPSTATE NY. Super 8.
Lesbian Gathering, In woods & house at Jill Johnston's upstate New York [Accord, NY?]. Unedited. Dark footage of faces. Good ball Game. Louise Fishman and others. In woods. Darker footage. Jill Johnston with Gay tee shirt and others. CU darker Jill. MS Jill.
Leader. Backlit. Looks like Jill dancing, acting up. Nice shots of dark figures of women backlit playing ball. Good outdoor shots of Jill. Jill hugging Jane O'Wyatt. Jill standing by V.W. bus wearing huge Peace symbol. slightly soft focus. Jacket hanging on bus, zoom out to Jill. CU's good of Jill.
Leader. Group inside house, Jane, and others. Sitting in circle. Dark. Someone sitting under desk lamp. (a few burnt frames) Jill outside by bus/van. (color in this reel looks sepia.) Good shot Louise Fishman with big hair!. Film broke and taped (repair before projecting next) at very end.
95. "ESTHER, LOUISE, ROBERTA, MARTHA: AUG. '71". 3 min. [Esther Newton, Louise Fishman, Roberta Kosse, Martha Shelley]
Women in nature. At creek. First part well exposed, middle black, end of feet CU well exposed.
96. FRIENDSHIP CIRCLE AT BEACH HOUSE A. Super 8, magnetic soundstripe film. May be sound.
Women in nature reading, another woman at a house. Looks like the same women in other films we've seen before. At a beach house. Goes w/something else. Some women are lying on beach towels. Woman who wrote Lover [Bertha Harris]?
97. FRIENDSHIP CIRCLE B. 1972, color Super 8
Phyllis in film. Starts w/shot of Phyllis Birkby. In good shape, looks like it's her group again, her friends. A shot of Phyllis in bellbottoms, 7/72. She has long hair, aviator glasses. Back of her head w/this other friend who we've seen in many movies, then of her w/light meter. She's holding a still camera. She's walking by the other woman, touches her, adjusts her hair. Slightly overexposed w/intermittent scratch, not bad, wearing red bellbottoms. Shows her in relationship to her group of friends at this beach house. Terrier dog w/red bandana around neck. Another shot of Phyllis w/hands on chest sticking out her tongue, turning and going into the house. Another shot of her outside the house, making hand gestures. Short bit of really nice exposure of her medium CU.
Another woman at door of the house in long shot. Same woman w/car in background, seated in the grass by the road. Another woman in lounge chair, lying on the beach. Lighting cigarette. CU of Bertha Harris, I think, nicely shot through the grasses, CU of her w/house in background.
98. THE GIRL GANG.
Woman w/Polaroid camera. Another woman in beach chair talking. Image is not scratched, nicely exposed, soft colors. Louise Fishman with red scarf sleeping on the ground. Somebody else reading on a blanket on the grass. Same group that was in # 33? at the potato chip eating. Sidney Abbott, I think. Study of women's hands, like she cut off their heads and just shot their hands. Colors are pastel. Woman smoking at end.
99. "GROUP". Super 8, 3 min.
Phyllis at beach with curly headed woman; looks like Provincetown beach or Long Island with snow on sand. Group of women walking, running. Cute group shot at end/Phyllis holding uprooted tree. Playful, well-exposed, 1 intermittent scratch, not bad.
100. GROUP. Sup.8, 3 min.
CU of group interior. well exposed. Then out at same beach as Reel #26. One does handstand.
101. "JANE AND JILL". Super 8. 3 minutes.
Much of closeups out of focus. Good infocus shots of Jane drawing; Jill exercising; Jill Johnston doing backbends. Outside in snow with bus in background, Jill's feet in the air. Jane nicely lit, sitting. Jill hugging Jane inside at table. Ouside in snow with bus looks like it's Jane's feet in air with Jill helping her do a headstand.
102. JILL JOHNSTON AND JANE O'WYATT. B&W 16 mm. original.
About a stop overerxposed. Person raking leaves [Huntington, MA]. Jane O'Wyatt and Jill Johnston. Cute of Jane raking leaves on the lawn. Fast funny action of Jill Johnston. No scratches, perfect condition and a shot with two of them raking in the same frame. Still shot of them standing posed w/rakes looking at each other.
Pan of Jill sitting on the ground next to Jane, quite overexposed. Interior almost perfect. Two frames of Jill w/pen, interior, and then whole shot is good exposure of Jill, posed to write, talking and Jane at side, talking back and forth. Jane scratching her arm while talking. Jill w/head in her hands and the book on the table is Women And Film, magazine. Graphic saying Oh, Wow! Shot of a stool w/someone's hand on it.
103. JENNIFER'S BIRTHDAY PARTY, 6/67.
Jennifer looks to be about 6 years old. Opens w/ her Happy Birthday song. Just a birthday party.
104. JILL JOHNSTON AND VAN 3/72.
Jill Johnston, soft focus. Really nice shot as camera pulls back, not scratched, nice light, looks like she's in a cabin. Date 3/72 on film. Shot out window, scratches on film. Snow on trees. Some shot she's trying to shoot that's dark lit. Jill's VW bus in the snow, shoots from different angles. Soft focus trees.
105. MARYLAND II. Reg. 8, color.
Good shape, good color. Reeds at ocean. A pier, reeds, white boathouse, pier leading back to big white mansion house. Family home? Horses. Kid on the beach. Cute woman posing in doorway. Light struck. Wonder if it's her sister.
Walking down steps. Showing off. Holding a coat. Same woman as on first Maryland tape. Has Phyllis' broad face.
Asian American woman. [Ming-Chi Wang??] Half is Maryland. Other half is Asian American woman, really cute, she's smoking, light is nice on her face. She's in a park. She's standing with an African American woman on the sidewalk and Phyllis has stocking cap and pea coat on. ***Great shot of Phyllis in a coat, in the park in fall, has a yellow lining to the scarf or to the coat. Brown hair, walks by the camera. It might be Central Park. Somebody lying on the grass, can't tell who. Asian woman again is dancing in the park and she's acting like she's behind the bars of a gate, putting her lips through as if she were blowing a kiss. Framed by the gate. New location, sort of like, don't know where, like Canal Street. Second story held up by wood pillars, row of 50 doors acting as wall on second floor. Very interesting. Pans doors.
106. OLD PEEKSILL CALENDAR. Super 8 mm. 1976. 20 seconds.
3 shots of Phyllis and other women nude on a lawn. Good exposure. Date on package reads 1975.
107. "PEEKSKILL LESLIE [NANCY?]/DINAH". Sup. 8
Dark, group of women undressing, CU of two women's faces that are correctly exposed. Two women on beach towel. Beautifully lit shot of badminton player, black background w/face and arms lit by the sun and companion. Playing badminton in the nude. Really great. With beachball behind. Looks like a two-woman badminton game. Perfect condition. Game over. Two women have arms around each other. As they bend over. One has silver chain above her ass. Other has levis on. New game. More than two people. Nude twosome. Playing topless. Overexposed shot of lawn and woman w/badminton racket. Then a nicely exposed one. Croquet in the nude, now leapfrog or wrestle. I would like to work w/this footage. Very idyllic, very 70s.
108. "PT. PLEASANT" 12/67. Super 8 color.
Architects around a model. Color looks really good. No scratches at all. Outside at a boat shed. Looking at the casement that holds back the sand. Boathouse on piers. Older woman w/mink collar and Christmas wreath at door. Older man (could be her parents). Nicely shot, he is smiling. Next section is black.
109. "R, K, W, CATS". B&W Sup. 8
Mysterious shot of woman's head going back and forth by cabinet. Woman w/bottle. Soft exposure. Woman pouring wine, think it's a woman, dark. African-American woman head shot and same other person. Cats are well exposed. Couple of cats on a wooden floor. Partial scratch in the film. More and more cats. Head shots of cats. Cats playing, rolling together on the floor.
110. SELF-PORTRAIT: HELLO, HELLO, HELLO, HELLO. Super 8. Approx. 2 min.
This is absolutely precious. Phyllis with short bob; with glasses, without, with hair back; with nun's cowl; with nun's cowl and prayer pose; hiding face; masked; side hat; smiling.
111. "SOFTBALL. (color)
Close up of woman smoking, zoom out. Softball game, in long shot, camera is along first base line. Shot of women in park benches, behind fence. Camera pans across. The pitcher confers with the catcher. Camera is behind plate, woman gets hit and runs to first base. Zoom in to close up of slip of paper with score. Med. long shot of three women conferring. Med. long shot of one woman helping another with practice swing. Goes blurry. More softball. One run, one strike. Tracking shot of pitcher throwing ball. Long shot of woman waiting at base. Another hit, pan shot between pitcher's mound and home base. Long shot of players walking off of field, hugging. Close up of women, talking. Medium shots of women embracing. Med. long shot of woman (Kate Millett?), arms extended, moving side to side. Another game, possibly soccer, in background. Long shot of women horsing around.
112. STREET FAIR. With woman (Leslie?). 3 min. Super 8.
Edited in camera. Nice shot of people walking past metal store shutters. Well exposed. Phyllis Birkby herself right after the shutters. Nice shot. More shutters. Long shot of Birkby by booth. Phyllis walks by loading dock. Leslie (?) walks by shutters; then in midst of fair. This short film looks edited.
113. "TOWER, ESTHER, LOUISE". Sup. 8, 3 min. 2 scratches in middle.
Louise Fishman. Phyllis (out of focus CU's) Good of Louise in bathing suit. At beach. Phyllis with 35mm camera. Phyllis in bathing suit. Esther, too. Tower must be the dog
114. "WOODSTOCK POOL; DANA'S BASEBALL TEAM.. [Dana Birkby, nephew]
Begins w/baseball game. Looks like a little league game, maybe women, no kids. Young boys' baseball team. No scratches, nicely exposed. Woodstock Pool: girl swimming in pool, fly in pool, girl on lounge, boy on lounge, adolescent boy walking, water splashing, guy diving, guys in pool, standing on shoulders, three guys making a tower on shoulders.
POLITICAL
115. "ABORTION ST. PAT'S. Protest ABORTION RIGHTS: ST. PATRICKS PROTEST. 3 min. good exposure.
116. "ABORTION. ABORTION RIGHTS: ST. PATS, REEL #2. 3 min. good exp.
117. ALBANY MARCH.(color) Either slightly out of focus, or the projector was having problems.
Shots of people walking together--from back. Medium shot of women; two more of these. Shot of banner. Blurry shots of women walking hand in hand, marching. Camera zooms in on faces, then pulls back for a wide shot. Wide shot of 3 or so people sitting on trunk of car, parade passes between them and the camera. Short strip of unexposed film. Wide shot from back, of marcher's heads and the banner flying overhead. Close up of linked hands and arms. Very dark exposure: front shot of marchers moving forward, close ups of individual faces. shot of Dyke banner. More blurry faces, linked hands. Side shot of marchers moving across the screen. Shots of two banners. Wide shot of marchers from slightly overhead.
118. "APRIL 10. DEMONSTRATION IN WASHINGTON, D.C.
Woman with FBI sign taking pictures. Man wearing pig mask and sign saying "Macho Pig." Fairly good but overexposed one stop and slightly scratched. Groups of people at rally. A photo enlarged of a man with graphics "Kidnapper" below. Peace icon flag. Woman with woman's lib symbol painted on cheek. Out of focus stuff. Woman with Asian Woman Photograph, woman has hand clasped. Cadets in uniform marching from behind. Colorful ragtag hippy looking marchers with colored flags walking toward camera. "Free Erika" Poster. Women with arms around one another protesting. Camera notes clothing. Women wear headbands of different colors. "Sisters Unite, You've nothing to Lose" signs. Cherry Blossom Festival signs indicates protest to free political prisoners is in Washington, D.C. Sisterhood banner. Guards at White House? Red graffiti on official walls: "Power to the underground sisters". "Support Sisters in Asia" banner. Lots of crowd, protester shots. All a little overexposed, but not too bad and slightly scratched, often one scratch through side or middle.
119. "DEC 12 DEMO. WOMENS' LIBERATION DEMONSTRATION. Dec. 12, NYC, 3 min.
Well Exposed. Free 24 Hour Childcare banner; women's lib poster/demands; CU of faces, pins, Ti-Grace Atkinson (?), some dark & out of focus.
120. "FIFTH STREET". Sup. B&W, approx. 10 min. Well preserved. [5th St. Women's Bldg takeover, Jan 1970]